Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Mary Fanton Roberts papers
- Dance and Theatre Correspondence/Subject Files, 1902-1953, undated, Series 5:; (Box 2-3; 0.8 linear feet)
  - Hamilton, Cosmo & Julie, 1930, 1942, undated (Reel D163, Frame 1280-1291)
  - Hampden, Walter & Mabel, 1915-1944 (Reel D163, Frame 1292-1308)
  - Humphrey, Doris, 1930, 1932, undated (Reel D163, Frame 707-712)
  - Irving, Isabel, 1909 (Reel D164, Frame 1-3)
  - Kahn, Otto H., 1926-1927 (Reel D164, Frame 4-5)
  - Kirstein, Lincoln, 1940-1941, undated (Reel D164, Frame 6-10)
  - Le Gallienne, Eva, 1925-1941, undated (Reel D164, Frame 11-28)
  - Le Gallienne, Richard, Irma & Julie, 1904-1941, undated (Reel D164, Frame 29-63)
  - Loftus, Cecelia, circa 1913-1940 (Reel D164, Frame 64-75)
  - Losch, Tilly, 1931, undated (Reel D164, Frame 76-77)
  - Lunt, Alfred, 1952, undated (Reel D164, Frame 78-84)
  - MacKaye, Percy, 1913-1917, 1945, 1949 (Reel D164, Frame 85-103)
  - Morin, Pilar, 1910 (Reel D164, Frame 104-113)
  - National Federation of Theatre Clubs, 1912 (Reel D164, Frame 411-413)
  - Neighborhood Playhouse, 1915-1916, undated (Reel D164, Frame 414-416)
  - Nijinsky, Romola, 1916-1952 (Reel D164, Frame 114-146)
  - Parker, Louise N., 1912 (Reel D164, Frame 147-150)
  - The Players, 1913, 1923, 1924 (Reel D164, Frame 151-152)
  - Provincetown Players, 1916-1927 (Reel D164, Frame 446-458)
  - Punch & Judy Theatre, 1915 (Reel D164, Frame 459-464)
  - Row, Arthur, 1949, undated (Reel D164, Frame 153-159)
  - Shaw, Mary, 1909-1916, undated (Reel D164, Frame 160-170)
  - Skinner, Cordelia & Otis, 1915, undated (Reel D164, Frame 171-177)
  - St. Denis, Ruth, 1945 (Reel D164, Frame 178-179)
  - Terry, Ellen, 1911, 1916 (Reel D164, Frame 180-183)
  - Theatre Guild, 1918-circa 1933 (Reel D164, Frame 184-200)
  - Untermyer, Mrs. Samuel (Minnie), 1911-1923, undated (Reel D164, Frame 230-256)
  - Walker, Stuart, 1915, 1919, undated (Reel D164, Frame 486-488)
  - Washington Square Players, 1915, undated (Reel D164, Frame 489-496)
  - Wigman, Mary, 1929-1931, undated (Reel D163, Frame 772-790)
  - Miscellaneous, A-C, 1910-1945 (Reel D164, Frame 262-300)
  - Miscellaneous, D, 1909-1937, undated (Reel D164, Frame 304-337)
  - Miscellaneous, Dance Material (1 of 3), 1910-1950, undated (Reel D163, Frame 610-706)
  - Miscellaneous, Dance Material (2 of 3), 1910-1950, undated (Reel D163, Frame 713-771)
  - Miscellaneous, Dance Material (3 of 3), 1910-1950, undated (Reel D163, Frame 791-841)
  - Miscellaneous, E-K, circa 1911-1938, undated (Reel D164, Frame 362-393)
  - Miscellaneous, L-M, 1915-1930, undated (Reel D164, Frame 394-410)
  - Miscellaneous, N-P, 1915-1936, undated (Reel D164, Frame 417-445)
  - Miscellaneous, R-T, 1916-1937, undated (Reel D164, Frame 465-485)
  - Miscellaneous, W-Z, 1916, undated (Reel D164, Frame 497-506)
- Literary and Music Correspondence/Subject Files, 1900-1952, undated, Series 6:; (Box 3; 0.6 linear feet)
  This series contains correspondence and other material documenting Mary Fanton Roberts' friendships with authors, poets, critics, publishers, singers, musicians, and colleagues. Found are letters, invitations, calling cards, programs, artwork, photographs, and news clippings. Topics of discussion include social invitations, poems and articles in the Craftsman or Touchstone Magazine, travel accounts, and general news. Correspondence of note is with poets Bliss Carman and Sir Charles G. D. Roberts, journalist Jacob Riis, theater patron Mrs. "Teuila" Salisbury Field, singers Yvette Guilbert and Marguerite Namara, author Kate Douglas Wiggin, author and "Rough Rider" Edwin Emerson, writer and entrepreneur Paris Singer, writers Ernest and Grace Seton, and author and good friend Lloyd Osbourne, stepson of Robert Louis Stevenson. Also found are photographs of authors Theodore Dreiser, Edwin Emerson, and Bliss Carman, handwritten poems by Theodore Goodridge Roberts, and a lithograph portrait of author John Masefield.
  - Atherton, Gertrude, 1912, undated (Reel D164, Frame 515)
  - Bambino, 1909-1921 (Reel D164, Frame 516-531)
  - Bispham, David, 1909-1912 (Reel D164, Frame 532-534)
  - Brooks, Van Wyck, 1910 (Reel D164, Frame 535-536)
  - Burgess, Gelett, 1904, 1920, undated (Reel D164, Frame 537-541)
  - Burnett, Frances Hodgson, 1905-1908, undated (Reel D164, Frame 542-554)
  - Bynner, Witter, undated (Reel D164, Frame 555)
  - Carman, Bliss, 1902-1933, (2 folders) (Reel D164, Frame 556-662)
  - Cobb, Irvin S., 1916, 1928, 1944, undated (Reel D164, Frame 663-672)
  - Comfort, Will Levington, 1914-1915 (Reel D164, Frame 673-685)
  - Damrosch, Walter, 1950, undated (Reel D164, Frame 686-690)
  - Dawson, Coningsby, 1914 (Reel D164, Frame 691)
  - Desti, Mary, 1925 (Reel D164, Frame 692-693)
  - Dreiser, Theodore, 1934, 1940, undated (Reel D164, Frame 694-715)
  - Eastman, Max & Eliena, 1944-1945 (Reel D164, Frame 716-718)
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1914 (Reel D164, Frame 719-720)
  - Emerson, Edwin, 1902-1948, undated (Reel D164, Frame 721-761)
  - Field, Mrs. Edward Salisbury (Teuila), 1903-1949 (Reel D164, Frame 762-864)
  - Gale, Zona, 1921 (Reel D164, Frame 865-867)
  - Galsworthy, John, 1919 (Reel D164, Frame 868-871)
  - Garland, Hamlin, 1915-1922, undated (Reel D164, Frame 872-880)
  - Guilbert, Yvette, 1916-1919, 1938 (Reel D164, Frame 881-895)
  - Hoffenstein, Samuel & Edith, 1929-1932, 1947 (Reel D164, Frame 896-904)
  - Hurst, Fannie, 1926-1937 (Reel D164, Frame 905-914)
  - Kilmer, Joyce, 1915 (Reel D164, Frame 915)
  - Khayat, Khalil, undated (Reel D164, Frame 916)
  - Literary Digest, 1922, 1925, 1940, undated (Reel D162, Frame 1350-1354)
  - McClure, S. S., 1915, 1949 (Reel D164, Frame 917-918)
  - Mannes, Mrs. David (Clara), circa 1935-1949, undated (Reel D164, Frame 919-945)
  - Masefield, John, 1912, 1918 (Reel D164, Frame 946-947)
  - Maxim, Hudson, 1903-1908 (Reel D164, Frame 948-952)
  - Metropolitan Opera Association, 1916, 1933, 1943 (Reel D164, Frame 953-966)
  - Namara, Marguerite, 1940-1944, undated (Reel D164, Frame 967-977)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1908-1916 (Reel D164, Frame 978-1046)
  - Osbourne, Lloyd & Ethel, 1902-1947, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1047-1063)
  - Oskison, Hildegarde Hawthorne, 1906-1929, 1952, undated (Reel D163, Frame 63-76)
  - Riggs, Mrs. George C. (Kate Dougles Wiggin), 1912, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1064-1068)
  - Riis, Jacob, 1914 (Reel D164, Frame 1069-1071)
  - Roberts, Sir Charles G. D., 1900-1943 (Reel D164, Frame 1072-1136)
  - Roberts, Theodore Goodridge, 1926-1939, undated (Reel D161, Frame 928-962)
  - Seton, Ernest Thompson & Grace, 1902-1936, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1137-1158)
  - Sinclair, May, 1924, 1946 (Reel D164, Frame 1159-1162)
  - Singer, Paris, 1916-1946, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1163-1222)
  - Stevenson, Mrs. Robert Louis, 1903-1951, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1223-1244)
  - Stokowski, Leopold, 1916 (Reel D164, Frame 1245)
  - Strong, Austin & Mary, 1918-1952 (Reel D164, Frame 1246-1261)
  - Teasdale, Sara, 1914 (Reel D164, Frame 1262-1263)
  - Towne, Charles Hanson, 1909-1944, undated (Reel D164, Frame 201-229)
  - Vorse, Mary Heaton, 1910 (Reel D164, Frame 1264)
  - West, Rebecca, 1923-1927, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1265-1272)
  - Widdemer, Margaret, 1913, 1938 (Reel D164, Frame 1273-1275)
  - Wilcox, Ella Wheeler, 1909 (Reel D164, Frame 1276-1277)
  - Wilkinson, Marguerite, 1928, undated (Reel D164, Frame 1278-1280)
  - Young, Stark, 1944 (Reel D164, Frame 1281-1284)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1901-1951 (Reel D164, Frame 1285-1296)
- General Correspondence, 1898-1946, undated, Series 7:; (Box 3-4; 0.4 linear feet)
  General correspondence includes invitations, programs, calling cards, and thank you notes regarding general social and club events. Researchers should note that there is some overlap with the above series. Items are arranged alphabetically by person or organization.
  - A, 1912-1939, undated (Reel D162, Frame 96-145)
  - B, 1909-1940, undated (Reel D162, Frame 146-189)
  - C, 1909-1945, undated (Reel D162, Frame 190-222)
  - D-E, 1923-1940, undated (Reel D162, Frame 223-245)
  - F, 1906-1945, undated (Reel D162, Frame 246-290)
  - G, 1921-1943, undated (Reel D162, Frame 291-319)
  - H, 1919-1944, undated (Reel D162, Frame 320-368)
  - I-J-K, 1898-1941, undated (Reel D162, Frame 369-396)
  - L, 1906-1937, undated (Reel D162, Frame 397-410)
  - M, 1909-1938, undated (Reel D162, Frame 411-435)
  - N, 1908-1946, undated (Reel D162, Frame 436-494)
  - O-P, 1906-1945, undated (Reel D162, Frame 495-548)
  - R, 1902-1944, undated (Reel D162, Frame 549-574)
  - S-T, 1905-1940, undated (Reel D162, Frame 575-621)
  - U-V, 1912-1937, undated (Reel D162, Frame 622-637)
  - W-Z, 1903-1940, undated (Reel D162, Frame 638-676)
- Writings, 1915-1926, 1952, undated, Series 8:; (Box 4; 3 folders)
  Writings include a draft of an autobiographical essay written by Mary Fanton Roberts that was intended to become a published memoir. Also found in this series are guest lists and notes concerning events she was hosting as well as typescripts of several poems by Dorothy Gostwick Roberts, who wrote under the name Gostwick Roberts, and was a niece of William Carman Roberts. Items are arranged in chronological order within each folder.
  - Biographical Essay, "Point of View" by Mary Fanton Roberts, 1952 (Reel D161, Frame 9-61)
  - Guest Lists and Notes, 1915-1917, 1923-1924, undated (Reel D161, Frame 596-636)
  - Poetry by [Dorothy] Gostwick Roberts, 1924-1926, undated (Reel D161, Frame 913-927)
- Printed Material, 1899, 1909-1947, undated, Series 9:; (Box 4-5; 0.3 linear feet)
  Printed material documents Mary Fanton Roberts' writing career and social activities. Found here are various art exhibition catalogs, trade bulletins for the House and Garden magazine written by Roberts as the merchandise editor, magazines containing articles written by Roberts, news clippings, an article on Deadwood, Montana, blank postcards, and clippings of published poetry. Poetry is arranged alphabetically by author, all other items are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  - Art Exhibition Catalogs, 1910, 1922-1945, undated (Reel D163, Frame 407-453)
  - Article, "Deadwood Gold", 1922 (Reel unfilmed)
  - House and Garden Trade Bulletin, 1922-1923 (Reel D161, Frame 695-708)
  - Magazine, The Arts, 1921 (Reel D161, Frame 831-872)
  - Magazine, The Denishawn Magazine, 1925 (Reel D161, Frame 709-721)
  - News Clippings, Biographical, 1909-1947, undated (Reel D161, Frame 488-512)
  - News Clippings, Published Writings (1 of 2), 1915-1937 (Reel D161, Frame 664-694)
  - News Clippings, Published Writings (2 of 2), 1915-1937 (Reel D161, Frame 722-830)
  - Poetry Clippings, A-P, 1899, 1910-1944, undated (Reel D161, Frame 873-912)
  - Poetry Clippings, S-Y, 1920-1922, undated (Reel D161, Frame 963-969)
  - Postcards, undated (Reel unfilmed)
- Photographs, 1880-circa 1943, undated, Series 10:; (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
  Photographs include personal photographs of Mary Fanton Roberts, her family, and friends as well as autographed portraits given to her. Photographs of actors and actresses include portraits of theater actresses such as Leslie Carter and Mildred McLeod as well as photographs of scenes from plays. Also found here are photographs of nude male models taken by photographer Nickolas Muray. Other items in this series include three framed portraits of Roberts's mother, Isabelle Annable Fanton, and several tintype portraits which include individuals and groups of young men and women. All are unidentified, but two of the young women often photographed may be Mary and her sister Belle. Miscellaneous photographs of people include portraits and snapshots of family and friends, many of them are unidentified and may be photographs of Roberts. One item of note is a photograph of the artist John Twachtman. Also in this series are photographs of various places, including the Roberts house in Waterford, Connecticut and stereo cards of street scenes in Deadwood, South Dakota, where Roberts lived for a period of time as a child. Researchers should note that series 4, 5, and 6 also contain photographs, filed with the appropriate person or subject heading.
  - Actors and Actresses, undated (Reel D164, Frame 507-514)
  - Nude Male Models by Nickolas Muray, undated (Reel unfilmed)
  - Portraits, Isabelle Agnes Annable Fanton (M. F. R.'s Mother), undated (Reel unfilmed)
  - Tintype Portraits (may include M. F. R.), 1881, undated (Reel D162, Frame 15-16)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of People (1 of 4), 1880-1942, undated (Reel D162, Frame 17-30)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of People (2 of 4), 1880-1942, undated (Reel D162, Frame 31-39)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of People (3 of 4), 1880-1942, undated (Reel D162, Frame 40-46)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs of People (4 of 4), 1880-1942, undated (Reel D162, Frame 47-56)
  - Photographs of Places, 1909-1910, 1932, undated (Reel D162, Frame 57-95)
  - House in Waterford, Connecticut (Copyprints), circa 1943 (Reel unfilmed)
  - Stereo Cards of Deadwood, South Dakota, undated (Reel unfilmed)
- Artwork, 1906, undated, Series 11:; (Box 5; 3 folders)
  Artwork includes a small pencil portrait of Mary Fanton Roberts by John Butler Yeats, and other small drawings of people and animals by unidentified artists. Also found are four hand colored book illustrations of unknown origin.
  - Drawing of Mary Fanton Roberts by John Butler Yeats, 1906 (Reel Box 5, Frame Folder 16)
  - Drawings by Unidentified Artists, undated (Reel D163, Frame 454-463)
  - Hand-colored Book Illustrations, undated (Reel unfilmed)